George Wunder Cartoons
George Wunder Cartoons
1947-1970
Wunder, George,1912-1987.
27 linear ft.
Original daily and Sunday cartoons from the newspaper adventure strip Terry and the Pirates (1947-1970) and original cartoons and proofs from the strip Our Guest Star (1955).
148768
Biographical History
George Wunder (1912-1987) grew up in Kingston, New York and studied art via correspondence courses. He began his career in 1936 with the art department of Associated Press in New York City. After a tour of duty in the army (1942-1946), he submitted his work for consideration as a replacement for Milton Caniff on Terry and the Pirates. He got the job and remained with the strip until it ended in 1973, thus working on it longer than its creator. Initially he copied Caniff's style but gradually evolved a distinctive look of his own. George Wunder died in 1987.
George Wunder was a member of the National Cartoonists Society and received its Silver T-Square Award in 1970.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Wunder Cartoons collection consists of more than 3,100 original daily cartoons and more than 240 original Sunday cartoons from Terry and the Pirates (1947-1970). Daily cartoons are approximately 7 1/2 x 23 inches, while Sunday cartoons are approximately 19 1/2 x 28 1/2 in. All show traces of graphite; text is on pasteovers (some of which are detaching) and art is brush, pen and ink on illustration board. There is also a single weekly proof sheet (covers May 5-10, 1958) which is 11 1/4 x 17 1/2 in.
The collection also contains 2 color proofs and 4 original cartoons from the strip Our Guest Star (1955). This was a promotional strip featuring characters from Terry and the Pirates with cameo appearances from movie stars and other celebrities. Color proofs are approximately 5 1/2 x 14 in. and the original art is approximately 7 x 23 in. Original art is brush, pen and ink on illustration board, with traces of graphite.
Arrangement of the Collection
Daily and Sunday Terry and the Pirates cartoons are arranged separately in chronological order. The Our Guest Star cartoons are foldered separately and can be found at the head of the Sunday series.
Related Material
Terry and the Pirates material by Milton Caniff can be located in the
Milton Caniff Collection
and the
Vernon Greene Papers
.
has collections of more than 150 cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing. In addition, the Rare Books holdings include a number of published reprint collections of Terry and the Pirates; please refer to and search on "Terry and the Pirates" as title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Wunder, George, 1912-1987.; Chicago Tribune-New York News Syndicate.; Our guest star (comic strip); Terry and the pirates (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; Adventure stories -- Comic books, strips, etc.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Proofs (printed matter); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of George Wunder, 1968-1969.
Terry and the Pirates, 7/20/1958, gift of Susan W. Price, 2015.
Inventory
- Our Guest Star comic strip
  - Cartoons
    - Features Mary Martin, Jan 27, 1955 (Oversize 1)
    - Features Grace Kelly, Apr 19, 1955 (Oversize 1)
    - Features Bob Cummings, Oct 28, 1955 (Oversize 1)
    - Features Charlton Heston, Dec 29, 1955 (Oversize 1)
  - Color proofs
    - Features Mary Martin, Jan 27, 1955 (Oversize 1)
    - Features Grace Kelly, Apr 19, 1955 (Oversize 1)
- Terry and the Pirates comic strip, Click here for detailed inventory.
  - Daily cartoons
    - Daily cartoons, 1947 Aug-1953 Dec (Box 1)
    - Daily cartoons, 1954 Jan-1955 Aug (Box 2)
    - Daily cartoons, 1955 Sep-1956 Jan (Box 3)
    - Daily cartoons, 1956 Feb-1956 Jul (Box 4)
    - Daily cartoons, 1956 Aug-1957 Feb (Box 5)
    - Daily cartoons, 1957 Mar-1957 Oct (Box 6)
    - Daily cartoons, 1957 Nov-1958 Feb (Box 7)
    - Daily cartoons, 1958 Mar-1958 Jun (Box 8)
    - Daily cartoons, 1958 Jul-1958 Oct (Box 9)
    - Daily cartoons, 1958 Nov-1959 Mar (Box 10)
    - Daily cartoons, 1959 Apr-1959 Aug (Box 11)
    - Daily cartoons, 1959 Sep-1960 Jan (Box 12)
    - Daily cartoons, 1960 Feb-1960 Jun (Box 13)
    - Daily cartoons, 1960 Jul-1960 Dec (Box 14)
    - Daily cartoons, 1961 Jan-1961 Apr (Box 15)
    - Daily cartoons, 1961 May-1961 Aug (Box 16)
    - Daily cartoons, 1961 Sep-1961 Dec (Box 17)
    - Daily cartoons, 1962 Jan-1962 May (Box 18)
    - Daily cartoons, 1962 Jun-1962 Sep (Box 19)
    - Daily cartoons, 1962 Oct-1963 May (Box 20)
    - Daily cartoons, 1963 Jun-1963 Sep (Box 21)
    - Daily cartoons, 1963 Oct-1964 Jan (Box 22)
    - Daily cartoons, 1964 Feb-1964 Jun (Box 23)
    - Daily cartoons, 1964 Jul-1964 Nov (Box 24)
    - Daily cartoons, 1964 Dec-1965 Apr (Box 25)
    - Daily cartoons, 1965 May-1965 Aug (Box 26)
    - Daily cartoons, 1965 Sep-1966 Jan (Box 27)
    - Daily cartoons, 1966 Feb-1966 Sep (Box 28)
    - Daily cartoons, 1966 Oct-1966 Dec; 1968 Jan (Box 29)
    - Daily cartoons, 1968 Feb-1968 May (Box 30)
    - Daily cartoons, 1968 Jun-1968 Oct (Box 31)
    - Daily cartoons, 1968 Nov-1969 Feb (Box 32)
    - Daily cartoons, 1969 Mar-1969 Jun (Box 33)
    - Daily cartoons, 1969 Jul-1970 Jan (Box 34)
  - Sunday cartoons
    - Sunday cartoons, 1958 Feb-1959 Dec (Oversize 1)
      Sunday cartoon dated 7/20/1958, gift of Susan W. Price, 2015.
    - Sunday cartoons, 1960 Jan-1961 Dec (Oversize 2)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1962 Jan-1963 Sep (Oversize 3)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1964 Jun-1965 Dec (Oversize 4)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1966 Jan-1966 Dec (Oversize 5)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1967 Jan-1967 Dec (Oversize 6)